Register of the Ernest William Darling Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest William Darling papers,
1917-1960
47007
Darling, Ernest William, 1905-
9 manuscript boxes (3.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, pamphlets, leaflets, and clippings, relating to the communist movement, political conditions, labor, and housing in Great Britain.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1905 Born, London, England
1919 Leaves school and starts working in a booksellers warehouse
1921 Joins trade union
1926 Participates in British General Strike and edits a strike bulletin
1931-1936 Works on the staff of the New Fabian Research Bureau
1932-1946 Active in the Communist Party of Great Britain as militant, branch secretary, and contributor to party publications
1937-1939 Secretary to Legal Bureau, Hampstead Tenants' Defence League
1939-1940 Works for British civil defense program
1942-1943 Shop steward, Philco factory, London
1946 Leaves Communist Party
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 1947, with an increment added in 1981, the Ernest William Darling papers in the Hoover Institution Archives comprise a small but interesting collection of primary documents and printed matter, most of which pertain to the history of the Communist Party of Great Britain in the 1930s and 1940s. As such, these materials offer a glimpse into the organizational life of the party at a number of levels, from the central committee down to the local branch level, and they record both public campaigns and internal party debates during a period extending from the Depression through the end of World War II.
Born into a working class family, Darling became politically involved at an early age, and his activism subsequently included roles as a trade union delegate, tenants' rights campaigner, and party militant. Materials relating to each of these activities are organized within separate files in the collection (see COMMUNIST PARTY OF GREAT BRITAIN ORGANIZATIONAL FILE, HAMPSTEAD TENANTS' DEFENCE LEAGUE FILE, and PHILCO SHOP STEWARDS FILE).
While never a party theorist, Darling did write on a number of topics, with a special emphasis on issues of employment and housing (see SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series). A significant exchange of letters with the British Communist leader, Harry Pollitt, can be found in the CORRESPONDENCE series, and these letters enumerate the reasons that led Darling to leave the party in 1946. The PRINTED MATTER series contains a large number of pamphlets issued by the Communist Party of Great Britain, covering a wide variety of issues ranging from London municipal elections to international politics.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Communism.; Communism--Great Britain.; Housing--Great Britain.; Labor unions--Great Britain.; Great Britain.; Great Britain--Politics and government--20th century.; Communist Party of Great Britain.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1930-1953. (Box 1)
  Autobiography, checklists, and membership cards, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1937-1946. (Box 1)
  Letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1928-1960. (Box 1-3)
  Articles, letters to the editor, memoranda, notes, outlines, pamphlets, proposals, reports, and transcripts, arranged chronologically by title. Includes related correspondence
- Communist Party of Great Britain Organizational File, 1934-1946. (Box 3-4)
  Bulletins, clippings, correspondence, course materials, leaflets, memoranda, newsletters, notes, resolutions, and statements, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Hampstead Tenants' Defence League File, 1937-1943. (Box 4-5)
  Bulletins, clippings, constitution, correspondence, financial records, forms, leaflets, reports, and statements, arranged alphabetically by physical form, and other material arranged within a subject file
- Philco Shop Stewards Committee File, 1941-1942. (Box 5)
  Correspondence, leaflet, and minutes, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1923-1947. (Box 5-6)
  Clippings, financial records, leaflets reports, and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photograph, n.d. (Box 6)
  One print depicting Ernest William Darling(?)
- Printed Matter, 1920-1945. (Box 6-9)
  Bulletins, campaign literature, leaflets, pamphlets, and serial issues, largely relating to the Communist Party of Great Britain and other radical organizations
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1930-1953 (Box 1)
  - Autobiography, 1945. (Folder 1: 1)
    Two typescripts
  - Checklists of publications, n.d., (Some items listed are no longer part of the collection) (Folder 1: 2)
  - Membership cards, 1930-1953. (Folder 1: 3)
    Includes cards for the Communist Party of Great Britain
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1937-1946.
  Letters and enclosures
  - Unidentified, 1937-1944 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Campbell, John, 1942-1943 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Daily Worker, 1939-1945 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Layton, J. M., 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Mellor, William, 1933 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Parsons, Henry, 1944-1945 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Pollitt, Harry, 1942-1946 (Folder 1: 10)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1928-1960.
  Includes related correspondence
  - "Marxism and the War," n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
    Typescript
  - "Report of the Subcommittee on the Law of Distress," paper prepared for the Haldane Society, n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - "Who Opposes Full Employment?" n.d. (Folder 1: 13-14)
    Three typescripts
  - "The B.B.C. and Working-Class Education," Socialist Review, 1928 July. (Folder 1: 15)
    Printed copy
  - "The Present and Future Work of NFRB (New Fabian Research Bureau)," 1933 September 21. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Notes on The Daily Worker," 1933 October 22. (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Notes on the Discussion on the Labour Party's Foreign Policy," paper prepared for the New Fabian Research Bureau, 1934 February 27. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "A New Foreign Policy for the Labour Party," paper prepared for the New Fabian Research Bureau(?), 1934 June 11. (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Notes on Research into Local Housing Conditions," paper prepared for the New Fabian Research Bureau, 1935 February 11. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "The British Labour Party in Transition - 1935," 1935 February 14 (pseudonym used, D. E. Williams). (Folder 2: 6)
    Holograph notes and two typescripts
  - "The International Situation," statement written for a conference of the Socialist League, London, England, 1935 June 7. (Folder 2: 7)
  - The Two Classes, 1935 November. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Hampstead Housing," 1937 August 6. (Folder 2: 9)
  - "A Social Programme for Hampstead," 1937 September 12. (Folder 2: 10)
  - "TDL (Tenants' Defence League) Campaign for 1600 Houses," 1937 October 2. (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Assisted Wiring Scheme in Hampstead," 1938 May 18. (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Statement to Hampstead Borough Council in Support of the Petition of Kilburn Tenants," 1938 November 21. (Folder 2: 13)
  - Speech at a meeting of the Hampstead Borough Council, 1938 November 24. (Folder 2: 14)
  - Open letters on behalf of the Hampstead Tenants' Defence League, 1938 December. (Folder 2: 15)
  - Testimony given before the Distress for Rent Committee, Ministry of Health, London, England, 1939 March 1. (Folder 2: 16)
    Transcript
  - Speech at factory meeting of Philco workers, London, England, 1942 April 16. (Folder 2: 17)
  - "Land Control in the Future," Social Service News, 1942 November. (Folder 2: 18)
  - "Question of Reconstruction," 1942 December 3. (Folder 2: 19)
    Holograph and typewritten notes, and typescript (incomplete) with holograph corrections
  - "The Politics of the Beveridge, or British Revolutions in the Making," 1942-12-12
    - Correspondence and memoranda (Folder 2: 20)
    - Two typescripts (Folder 2: 21)
  - "Statement by E. W. Darling on the Report (by Hugh Mackay) on South West St. Pancras," London, England, 1943 May 31. (Folder 2: 22)
    Two typescripts and one transcript of ensuing discussion
  - "Notes on Franchise Law and Electoral Reform," 1943 December 5. (Folder 2: 23)
  - "The British Trade Union Movement of Today," 1944
    - Research material (Folder 2: 24)
    - Four typescripts (Folder 2: 25)
  - Electoral Reform, 1944 February 18. (Box 3)
    Proposals written by Ernest William Darling and presented to the House of Commons, London, England, by William Gallacher, Member of Parliament
    - Correspondence, outline, and typescript preliminary draft (Folder 3: 1)
    - Three typescripts (Folder 3: 2)
    - Printed copy (Folder 3: 3)
  - "Our National Traditions," article submitted to World News and Views, 1944 May 10 (not published). (Folder 3: 4)
    Correspondence and two typescripts
  - "Full Employment," 1944 May 28. (Folder 3: 5)
  - "National Debt and Full Employment," 1944 May 29. (Folder 3: 6)
    Typescript notes
  - "The 6th of June," 1944 June 7. (Folder 3: 7)
  - "The Government's Policy of Full Employment," 1944 June 15. (Folder 3: 8-10)
  - Memorandum concerning Lever Brothers and Unilever, 1945 May 16. (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Re Newcastle Council Tenants Association," 1945 June 27. (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Lease Lend, Full Employment and the Colonies," 1945 September 25. (Folder 3: 13)
  - Letter to the editor, World News and Views, 1945 November 11. (Folder 3: 14)
    Correspondence and typescript
  - Letter to the editor, Guardian (Manchester), 1960 March 10. (Folder 3: 15)
- COMMUNIST PARTY OF GREAT BRITAIN ORGANIZATIONAL FILE, 1934-1946
  - Clippings, 1934-1940 (Folder 3: 16-17)
  - Congress resolutions and statements, 1934-1946 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1946 (Box 4)
    - Central Committee, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Executive Committee, 1943-1945 (Folder 4: 2)
    - London District Committee, 1946 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Internal bulletins, memoranda, newsletters, and statements, 1934-1945 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Leaflets, 1934-1943 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Notes for speakers, 1934-1945 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Training course materials, 1935-1936 (Folder 4: 7)
- HAMPSTEAD TENANTS' DEFENCE LEAGUE FILE, 1937-1943
  - Bulletins, reports, and statements, 1938-1940 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Clippings, 1937-1943 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Constitution, 1938 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Financial records, 1937-1938 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Forms, n.d. (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Leaflets, 1937-1939 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Subject file, 1938-1940.
    Bulletins, correspondence, financial records, leaflets, reports, and resolutions
    - Stepney Tenants' Defence League, 1938-1939 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Federation of Tenants' and Residents' Associations, 1939-1940 (Folder 5: 4)
- PHILCO SHOP STEWARDS COMMITTEE FILE, 1941-1942
  - Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Leaflet, n.d. (Folder 5: 6)
  - Minutes
    - 1941-1942 (Folder 5: 7)
    - 1942 (Contd.) (Folder 5: 8-9)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1923-1947.
  Clippings, financial records, leaflets, reports, and serial issues
  - Fourth International (Folder 5: 10)
  - Independent Labour Party (Folder 5: 11)
  - Labour Party (Great Britain) (Folder 5: 12)
  - London Municipal Society (Folder 5: 13)
  - New Fabian Research Bureau (Folder 5: 14)
  - New Fabian Research Bureau (Contd.) (Folder 6: 1-2)
  - Trade-unions - Great Britain (Folder 6: 3)
  - Workers' Educational Association (Folder 6: 4)
- PHOTOGRAPH, n.d. (Folder 6: 5)
  One print depicting Ernest William Darling(?) as an adolescent with his family
- PRINTED MATTER, 1920-1945. (Folder 6: 6-8)
- PRINTED MATTER (Contd.) (Box 7-9)